Finding Aid for Patrice I. Elms Papers 1972-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Patrice I. Elms Papers 1972-1997, 1987-1992
Elms, Patrice I., 1943-
1.5 linear foot
Feminist, active in various women's rights organizations and causes; the files concerns her activities with American Association of University Women and the People's Campaign for Choice, 1987-1988; also included are Topical Files, 1972-1999 and Audiovisual Materials, 1986-1997
9975 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Patrice I. Elms in July 1999. (Donor no. 8854 ).
The collection is open for research.
Patrice I. Elms has championed women's rights issues in Michigan since the early 1980s. Elms, who resides in Marshall, Michigan, has held numerous offices with state women's associations. She has been president of her town chapter of the American Association for University Women (AAUW), state legislative chairwoman for the same organization, treasurer of the People's Campaign for Choice (reproductive rights) ballot question committee, and a lobbyist for women's pay equity. She is currently (1999) the president of the Michigan Women's Assembly, the statewide umbrella group for women's rights organizations.
Elms cites the failure of the Equal Rights Amendment as the catalyst of her political career. Elms was also active in the Marshall chapter of the AAUW, eventually becoming elected president and then moving on to become the organization's state legislative chairwoman. Elms vehemently lobbied state lawmakers on the subjects of education reform and abortion rights. She became the treasurer of People's Campaign for Choice in 1987, a referendum petition drive created to place a proposal on the November 1988 ballot to rescind Public Act 59 of 1987 which banned Medicaid-funded abortions. The group organized a petition drive to collect enough signatures to get the question placed on the ballot and raised funds to educate the public on the issue of reproductive health, reproductive rights and economic equity.
Elms received her bachelor's and master's degrees at Michigan State University and was an elementary educator for five years before entering state politics.
The papers of Patrice I. Elms, consisting of correspondence, reports, topical files and some organizational records, provide a fine overview of the state of abortion rights in Michigan in the later 1980s and other controversial issues such as school choice and parochiaid. The papers are arranged in four series: American Association of University Women, People's Campaign for Choice, 1987-1988, Topical, 1972-1999 and Audiovisual Materials, 1986-1997. These documents provide a fine overview of the state of abortion rights in Michigan in the later 1980s.
Subjects:
Abortion.; American Association of University Women.; Elms, Patrice I., 1943-; Feminists--Michigan.; Peoples Campaign for Choice.; Women's rights.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Abortion.; Elms, Patrice I., 1943-; Peoples Campaign for Choice.; Prayers in the public schools.; Promise Keepers (Organization)
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- American Association of University Women 1985-1992
  American Association of University Women, 1985-1992 is a small series comprised of files from various organizational activities and concerns ranging from nuclear war prevention efforts to the issue of teenage pregnancy.
  - Michigan Educational Equity Roundtable 1992 (Box 1)
  - Nuclear War Prevention 1985 (Box 1)
  - Teenage Pregnancy 1990-1991 (Box 1)
- People's Campaign for Choice 1987-1988
  People's Campaign for Choice, 1987-1988 includes files from Elms' career as the organization's treasurer. Researchers should be aware that Elms was treasurer of approximately fifteen similar fundraising committees (a list may be found in biographical material under Topical, 1972-1999) at this same time. While the overwhelming majority of the material contained in this series was generated by People's Campaign for Choice activities, some material hails from other committees.
  - Budget (Box 1)
  - Bylaws (Box 1)
  - Campaign Reports and Plans (Box 1)
  - Committee Minutes (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Fundraising (Box 1)
  - Legal Opinions (Box 1)
  - Murphine and Walsh (Box 1)
  - Personnel (Box 1)
  - Polling (Box 1)
  - Press Conference Packet (Box 1)
  - Referendum Petition Campaign (Box 1)
- Topical 1972-1999
  The Topical, 1972-1999 series includes information on education and abortion, two subjects Elms frequently brought to the attention of state lawmakers. This series also contains documentation of Elms' early involvement in her neighborhood organization, the Squaw Creek Neighborhood Association.
  - Abortion
    - Fact Sheets 1985-1989 (Box 1)
    - Magazine and Newspaper Articles 1978-1989 (Box 1)
    - Memoranda and Newsletters 1990 (Box 1)
    - Pamphlets and Brochures 1989 (Box 1)
    - Parental Consent Laws 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Pro-Choice Advocacy 1989-1991 (Box 1)
    - United States International Abortion Policies 1990 (Box 1)
  - Biographical Material (Box 1)
  - Education
    - Council of Organizations and Others for Education about Parochiaid 1995 (Box 1)
    - Marshall, Michigan Teachers' Strike 1987 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Educational Forum 1993 (Box 1)
    - Noah Webster Academy vs. Michigan Department of Education 1999 (Box 1)
    - Schools of Choice 1984-1992, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Individual Liberties Promotion 1990 (Box 2)
  - Michigan ERAmerica 1990-1992 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Women's Assembly (Box 2)
  - Michigan Women's Resource Guides 1989-1993 (Box 2)
  - Planned Parenthood 1989 (Box 2)
  - Squaw Creek Neighborhood Association 1972-1983 (Box 2)
  - United Nations Association, Lansing, Michigan branch 1985 (Box 2)
- Audiovisual Material 1986-1997
  Several photographs of Michigan legislators signing the People's Campaign for Choice petition and five videotapes make up Audiovisual Material, 1986-1997. The videotapes address subjects such as school prayer and abortion.
  - Photographs of legislators signing People's Campaign for Choice petition circa 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - Videotapes
    - "Advance Michigan: Vote No, Proposals A and C," 1992 (Box 2)
    - "Living Victims of Abortion," 1987 (Box 2)
    - "Promise Keepers, Equality Bashers," 1997 (Box 2)
    - Talk show, Patrice Elms on school prayer 1995 (Box 2)
    - Television advertisements on abortion rights 1986 (Box 2)